[MUSIC PLAYING]
Have you ever wondered how your cellphone
can detect objects and discriminate between boats
and a bridge?
Or were you ever surprised when Amazon
was able to recommend you a book that you didn't even
know that you wanted it.
So those are just two examples of what machine learning
technology can do for you today.
But imagine what it can do in all other areas of our lives.
And part of our job at MIT is actually
to imagine this future.
And here we're working on all different application
of machine learning and AI, ranging from drug discovery,
identifying who may be sick, or developing new robotics
applications, or helping people to live happier and longer.
So there are lots and lots of applications
out there, but what's so interesting about it--
that in terms of algorithms, there
is a relatively small toolkit of algorithms
you need to learn to understand how
these different applications can work so nicely
and be integrated in our daily life.
So that's what this class is about--
understanding this technology.
And I hope that, by the end of this class,
you would actually know how your cellphone can detect bridges.